(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.2",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
うわああああ！
WAAAAAAH!
やだああああ！
NOOOOOOOO!
うっ...
Ugh...
エイリアンエイリアン
Lyrics / Composition: ナユタン星人
Alien Alien
Lyrics & Composition: NayutalieN
Let's go!
ゆらゆらと　劈く　膿汁く
Swaying, tearing, festering
雨降れる感情
Rain-falling emotions
感覚のテレパス
Telepathy of the senses
迷子の二人はコンタクト
Two lost children make contact
心は恋を知りました
My heart has learned what love is
タイトロープ　ツギハギのせい
Tightrope, because of the patchwork
重度のディスコミュニケーション
Severe discommunication
眼光　赤色にキラキラ
My gaze glitters in crimson
何かが起こる　村雨
Something's about to happen in this passing shower
エイリアン　わたしエイリアン
Alien, I'm an alien
あなたの心を惑わせる
Bewildering your heart
交じりあう宇宙の引力で
With the mixing gravity of the universe
感じてる気持ちはトキメキ
The feeling I'm sensing is a throb
エイリアン　あなたのエイリアン
Alien, I'm your alien
引きあう心は逃れられない
Drawn hearts cannot escape each other
あなたに未体験あげる
I'll give you an experience like never before
異世界の果てまでトキメキ
A heart-throb to the end of a different world
スキ
I love you
点灯と消灯を繰り返してる蛍光灯
A fluorescent light repeating its flickering
超常な混沌が静まりかえる夜
A night where supernatural chaos falls silent
エイリアンエイリアン
Alien Alien
あなたを蝕んだ
It eroded you
迷宮の信号は
The signals of the labyrinth
特異点により交わった
Crossed paths at a singularity
創造事実も神秘を
Creative facts and mysteries
感情補正放った
Released emotional corrections
シンドローム　ひとりきり　夜な夜な
Syndrome, all alone, night after night
空想を　畳まるべく　リピート回る
Repeat turns to fold up the fantasies
幸は避ける　浮遊感　まだあなたは
A sense of floating that avoids happiness, you still
全てを知りたい
Want to know everything
エイリアン　私エイリアン　あなたの心を惑わせる
Alien, I'm an alien, leading your heart astray
瞳に映らない引力に　気づいてよ　私は
Notice the gravity that isn't reflected in your eyes, I am
エイリアン　あなたのエイリアン　触れ合えば傷は二度と消えない
Alien, your alien, if we touch, the wound will never vanish
降り注ぐ無数の隕石も　燃える心には届かない
Countless falling meteors cannot reach a burning heart
エイリアン　二人はエイリアン　高鳴る気持ちが抑えられない
Alien, we are aliens, can't suppress these throbbing feelings
あなたは未確認生命体　異世界の果てまで
You're an unidentified life form, to the ends of another world
あなたが 好き
I like you
3D!
Yofaria! Ah, kamera.
Yofaria! Ah, camera.
Sini.
Over here.
Halo! Ini udah kayak ya?
Hello! This is a bridge, right?
Satu ya, oke ya?
One, okay?
Ah, 3D boy.
Udah? Nggak apa-apa.
Is it done? It's okay.
Oke.
Okay.
大丈夫。
It's okay.
Halo!
Hello!
Yofaria!
Halo!
Hello!
Bridge. Bridge. Kayang. Oke.
Bridge. Bridge. Kayang. Okay.
Halo! Halo halo halo!
Hello! Hello hello hello!
Hai! Selamat datang di Airani Iofifteen 3D!
Hi! Welcome to Airani Iofifteen 3D!
Jangan lupa di apa, di-tweet ya.
Don't forget to, you know, tweet it.
#AiraniIofifteen3D pakai "I".
#AiraniIofifteen3D using an "I".
Kita udah dua tahun masih ada yang pakai "L" jadi "Lofifteen".
It's been two years and people still use 'L' instead of 'I', making it 'Lofifteen'.
So it's Airani Iofifteen with "I", not "L".
We've already been through this for two years, okay?
Okay?
Nah, halo! Yopi lihat lo komentarnya.
So, hello! Yopi sees your comments, you know.
Hai! Hai! Hai!
Hi! Hi! Hi!
Airani Iofifteen special day, so I really want to make this something really special...
...so please don't forget to tweet. Tweet お願いね？
...so please don't forget to tweet. Please tweet, okay?
ここだよ！
I'm over here!
Oke.
Okay.
Oke, kita mulai dari awal.
Okay, let's start from the beginning.
Halo, salam kenal Yofaria, Obis.
Hello, nice to meet you Yofaria and Obis.
Pagi... eh bukan pagi sih, malam.
Morning... wait, not morning, evening.
Malam! Aku Airani Iofifteen atau Yopi atau Yofii dari hololive Indonesia generasi pertama.
Evening! I'm Airani Iofifteen, or Yopi, or Yofii from hololive Indonesia's first generation.
Hi, I'm Yofii from hololive Indonesia first generation.
一期生のヨフィです、インドネシアの。ありがとうございます！
I'm Yofii from the first generation, from Indonesia. Thank you very much!
Hai!
Hi!
ということでね...
And so...
ようこそ！ようこそ！
Welcome! Welcome!
Lihat dong! Lihat dong!
Look at this! Look at this!
Luas dong!
It's so wide!
Di sini bisa lihat...
Over here you can see...
あ、あれね。イオフィのおうち。
Ah, that's it. Yofii's house.
Itu rumah Yopi ya, BTW ya.
That's Yopi's house, by the way.
あ、イオフィ一応お姫様だから。姫だから。
Ah, I'm technically a princess. Since I'm a princess.
I'm actually... if you don't forget, I'm a princess.
Look at that! That is my home, actually.
So yeah, 忘れないでね。あれイオフィの家。
So yeah, don't forget. That's Yofii's house.
Itu rumah Yopi.
That's Yopi's house.
Terus mau tahu nggak? Mau tahu nggak? Mau tahu nggak?
Then do you want to know? Do you want to know? Do you want to know?
Mau lihat nggak?
Do you want to see?
Oke, ada UFO. イオフィの... UFO!
Okay, there's a UFO. Yofii's... UFO!
どこだ？
Where is it?
Ini UFO-nya Yopi!
This is Yopi's UFO!
な？どう？可愛い可愛いでしょう？
See? How is it? It's cute, isn't it?
Lucu kan kayak Yopi?
It's cute like Yopi, right?
Lucu lho! Hai!
It's cute! Hi!
BTW ada yang mau request pose nggak?
By the way, does anyone want to request a pose?
ポーズリクエストある？あります？
Any pose requests? Anyone?
ない？
No?
Is there any pose request?
Enggak apa-apa kok, kalian ngetik juga kelihatan sama Yopi.
It's okay, Yopi can see what you're typing.
Apa? He-eh.
What? Uh-huh.
あ、UFOだ。UFOです。
Ah, it's the UFO. It's a UFO.
ん？なに？
Hmm? What?
Apa? He-eh.
What? Uh-huh.
あ！オッケーオッケーオッケー。
Ah! Okay okay okay.
Hai! T-pose nah.
Hi! T-pose, then.
今更T-poseはい。
A T-pose, now? Okay.
ん。可愛い。
Hmm. Cute.
T-pose T-pose デンデンデン。
T-pose T-pose den-den-den.
ジョジョ。
JoJo.
ジョジョのこれ。あ、これあの...
This JoJo one. Ah, this one is...
反逆の。オワラワワ。
The rebellion one. Owarawawa.
やべ、どうしよう！
Oh no, what should I do!
できない！
I can't do it!
オワラワワ。できないよ。
Owarawawa. I can't do it.
T-pose.
Kayang udah.
The bridge pose is done.
Anything else? Anything else?
何かある？
Is there anything?
ジョジョとあのブリッジ以外の...
Other than JoJo and that bridge pose...
Arus? Arus?
Is it flowing? Is it flowing?
Kayang udah.
I've already done the bridge pose.
あー、もしもし。
Ah... hello?
まあいっか。とりあえず次の場所行く行く見たい見たい？
Oh well. Anyway, do you want to go to the next place?
Kayaknya mereka udah siap satu lagi.
Looks like they've got another one ready.
Okay? Mau lihat? Mau lihat?
Okay? Want to see? Want to see?
Okay, let's go to the next place.
See you!
NOW LOADING
ほ？え？どこ？
Ho? Eh? Where?
あれ？えりまなし？おいこら！
Huh? Eri-manashi? Hey, you!
Sini!
Come here!
Come down, come here, here, here. Sini!
Come down, come here, here, here. Come here!
What? Sini!
What? Come here!
どこ？Come... ちょっと... こっち。
Where? Come... just... this way.
あ、あ... Okay, sini!
Ah, ah... Okay, come here!
あ、いい子いい子こっち。いい子、いい子こっち。
Ah, good boy, good boy, this way. Good boy, good boy, this way.
どこ？
Where?
こんあるし！
Kon-arushi!
おい！
Hey!
じゃん！
Jan!
違う！
Wrong!
Di belakang, di belakang, di sini. Ah, ah, ah.
Behind, behind, here. Ah, ah, ah.
Here, here, here boy, here boy, here boy.
Come here. Where? Oh!
違う！
No!
ごめん！真ん中。ま・ん・な・か。
Sorry! The middle. Mid-dle.
Sini tengah, tengah, tengah di sini.
Here in the middle, middle, middle here.
Hmm...
ばー！
Baa!
Sini! こっち！
Here! This way!
こっち！
This way!
あれ？
Huh?
もう、まり、こっち！
Geez, Mari, this way!
Hmm, dah ayo.
Hmm, let's go.
Ta-da!
そこかよ！
So it was there!
Sini! こんあるし... stop it!
Here! Kon-arushi... stop it!
こん... di sini! Sini!
Kon... here! Here!
Ah, ah, ah...
Here, here boy, here boy.
Sini!
Here!
Here boy, here boy.
あ、くら、くら、くら。
Ah, kura, kura, kura.
Sini!
Here!
おい、あ、か...
Hey, ah, ka...
...sini, sini.
...here, here.
おー、え、え。
Oh, eh, eh.
まあいっか！
Oh well!
おー、日々は知らない！
Oh, I don't know the days!
へ？どこ？
Huh? Where?
今更！
Now of all times!
まあいっか！
Oh well!
Bye!
Hun.
あー！
Ah!
は！さかな！
Ha! Fish!
ちあなごー！
Garden eel!
Halo! Ketemu lagi dengan Yopi! Hai!
Hello! Met with Yopi again! Hi!
Jadi ini kita bukan gudang. Bukan gudang.
So here we are not in a warehouse. Not a warehouse.
Ya, ini... this is my atelier.
Yes, this is... this is my atelier.
This is my studio. これスタジオだね？
This is my studio. This is the studio, right?
Bukan gudang.
Not a warehouse.
Tapi ya si Yopi turun di sini tapi nggak mandi di sini sih...
But yeah, Yopi landed here but doesn't shower here...
...tidur di sini, makan di sini, iya.
...sleep here, eat here, yes.
Tapi kita mau lihat ya...
But we want to see...
...ini by the way yang kalian lihat di belakang...
...by the way, what you see behind...
...ini adalah yang dipakai di MV High Five.
...these are what were used in the High Five MV.
これだね、私たち一期生の「High Five」の曲の出てきたのがこれなのね...
These are it, the ones that appeared in our 1st Gen song 'High Five'...
...この部分。
...this part.
Can you see it? Can you see it?
So this is actually... I can come here, okay.
So this is actually the first drawing I made for Moona for her 100k.
100... yeah. 100,000 subscribers...
...yang Yopi bikin buat Moona 100 ribu subs.
...that Yopi made for Moona's 100k subs.
Nah, ini lagi, kecil-kecil.
Now, this one again, the small ones.
Nah, ini adalah remastered version...
Now, this is the remastered version...
...dari pertama kali Yopi apa sih? Gambar pertama pas debut.
...of the first time Yopi, what was it? The first drawing from my debut.
これね、デビューしたころの最初の絵かな。
This is, like, the first drawing from around my debut.
あのもっとSD版のやつ。
The SD version of it.
とね、まだいるかな？
And, is it still there?
いる？ここ、ここ、こっち、こっち、こっち来る？
Is it there? Here, here, this way, this way, will you come here?
Ta-da! ママ見てる？ママ見てる？
Ta-da! Mom, are you watching? Mom, are you watching?
これね、あの去年のママの誕生日のための絵なんですよ。
This is the drawing for Mom's birthday last year.
Ini apa, gambar yang Yopi buat waktu ini buat ulang tahunnya mama.
This is, like, the drawing Yopi made at this time for Mom's birthday.
Nah! てて！
Now! So wholesome!
自分で言うんだけど、てて！
I'm saying it myself, but so wholesome!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
あー！あどぅ、ちゃぺ。ちゃぺ。
Ah! Oh, I'm tired. Tired.
Lucu kan? Lucu kan? Lucu kan?
Cute, right? Cute, right? Cute, right?
Okay, nah, tapi kan kita udah di studio nih.
Okay, now, since we're in the studio...
スタジオにいるからさ、お絵描きしたくない？
...since we're in the studio, don't you want to draw something?
Hmm? Do you want to draw something while in this studio?
I think, right right? Yes guys.
Bentar deh, Yopi cari sesuatu untuk buat gambar.
Wait a sec, Yopi's looking for something to draw with.
Okay. 探そう...
Okay. Let's look...
...えっと、お絵描き、お絵描き、お絵描き、お絵描き。
...um, drawing, drawing, drawing, drawing.
お！あった！
Oh! Found it!
Ada guys, ada guys.
It's here guys, it's here.
Ini siapa sih yang simpen di atas?
Who put this up here?
Mちゃん！助けて、高すぎ！
M-chan! Help, it's too high!
It's too high for me! あー、どうしよう。
It's too high for me! Ah, what should I do?
Hmm! Hmm!
やー！
Yah!
Aduh, Yopi, Yopi, Yopi pasti bisa. Yopi apa oh bisa. Ah udah.
Oh, Yopi, Yopi, Yopi can do it for sure. Yopi can do anything. There.
Eh, apa? Pendek-pendek apa? I'm not too short. Okay.
Eh, what? What do you mean short? I'm not too short. Okay.
Yopi oh bisa.
Yopi can do it.
せーの、ふぁ！
Ready, set, go!
あ、あ、できた！
Ah, ah, I did it!
Okay. よ... よいしょ。
Okay. Yo... heave-ho.
Ah, bisa dong.
Ah, of course I can.
Hai! Hai! Hai!
Hi! Hi! Hi!
Gimana nih? Gede kan?
How is it? It's big, right?
This is actually kind of like a little bit too big for me. Oh guys.
Okay. どうしよ、どうしよ。お絵描きするよ、やっぱね。
Okay. What should I do, what should I do. I'm going to draw, as expected.
ということで今日はね、これで、これでお絵描きしたいと思います！
So today, I'm going to draw with this, with this!
Jadi Yopi hari ini mau menggambar pakai ini.
So Yopi is going to draw with this today.
Jan jan! Jan jan!
Ta-da! Ta-da!
Ini udah ada. Wih!
It's already here. Whoa!
Pendek? Bukan pendek! Ininya kegedean. Moh!
Short? I'm not short! This thing is just too big. Geez!
IOが小さいわけじゃない。もう、これが大きすぎるもん。大きすぎるもん。
It's not that I'm small. It's just that this is too big. It's too big.
Oke. Gedean? Sss... diam.
Okay. Too big? Sss... be quiet.
ということで、これがあるから、ペイント、ペイント。あ、ここにある。OK.
So, since I have this, let's paint, paint. Ah, it's over here. OK.
ん、どうしよ... うう...
Hm, what should I do... ugh...
うわぁ！ははは！
Uwah! Hahaha!
いよっしょ！あぁ！
Heave-ho! Ah!
え？
Eh?
え、どうすればいいんだろ、これ。うぃっ！
Eh, what should I do with this? Whoa!
Mampus, mampus, asik.
Damn, damn, fun.
Eh? Eh? Tapi kamu yang di sana kok kamu bersih? Ih kok kamu bersih sih?
Eh? Eh? But why are you guys over there so clean? Why are you guys so clean?
そこのあなた、なんか綺麗だね。
You over there, you look so clean.
やっちゃう？これっちゃう？ It's kind of like pretty, don't you think?
Shall I do it? You want some? It's kind of like pretty, don't you think?
You want to get paint? You want to get painted?
もう、草じゃないよ！
Jeez, it's not 'kusa'!
お、じゃあ行くよ、みんなは、みんなもね、くらえ！
Oh, well then here I go! Everyone, you guys too... take this!
ひゃ！ひゃ！ぴゃ！ひゃ！うわぁ！
Hya! Hya! Pya! Hya! Huah!
はぁ！ははは！じゃ！
Ha! Hahaha! Bye!
Ya, beneran kalian tadi, gimana? Gimana, gimana?
Yeah, really, you guys just now, how was it? How was it, how was it?
Tadi Yopi gimana? Hm? Hm? Enak? Mau lagi?
How was Yopi just now? Hm? Hm? Good? Want more?
Oke.
Okay.
Yeah, one more time, one more time? Yes, yes!
きゃあ！きゃあ！ははは！
Kya! Kya! Hahaha!
行く？もう一回？
Shall we go? One more time?
おっけー、もう一回やるって。みんながこれが好きだって。
Okay, I'll do it one more time. Everyone says they like this.
じゃあ行くよ！さらに、くらえ！ひゃ！ひゃ！ひゃ！ひゃ！あぁー！
Well then here I go! Take even more of this! Hya! Hya! Hya! Hya! Aah!
Gimana deh? Tadi... Tadi... Oke, udah deh.
How was it? Just now... Just now... Okay, that's enough.
ということで本気で、本気でお絵描きします！
So, I'm going to draw seriously now, seriously!
Jadi Yopi mau menggambar beneran.
So Yopi is going to draw for real.
待ってね、ここね... よいしょ。
Wait, here... heave-ho.
ふふふ... しゅっしゅっしゅっ... うぅ... しゅっしゅっしゅっ...
Fu fu fu... sss sss sss... ugh... sss sss sss...
良いバリア？ Lope... love love... よいしょ。はい、とんとん。
Good barrier? Love... love love... heave-ho. Okay, tap tap.
よいしょ。あぁ... おっけー、おっけー！
Heave-ho. Ah... okay, okay!
できた、できたぽい、できたぽい、できたぽい！できたー！
I did it, I did it-pai, I did it-pai, I did it-pai! I did it!
見る？見る、見る、見る？んー見る？見る？おっけー、じゃあ...
Want to see? Want to see, see, see? Hm, want to see? Want to see? Okay then...
できたった！できた？できちゃった！
It's done! Is it done? It's done!
見る見るー！しゅっ... あぁ！あぁ！ははは！
Look, look! Zoom... ah, ah! Hahaha!
Halo, ini IOFORIA. Lope lope. Hebat.
Hello, this is IOFORIA. Love love. Great.
Da, da, かわいよ。かわいよ. Lucu nggak? Lucu nggak? Lucu dong.
There, there, isn't it cute? It's cute. Isn't it cute? Isn't it cute? Of course it is.
Tapi yang gambar lebih lucu nggak? へーえ。Lucu!
But isn't the one who drew it cuter? Heee. Cute!
Lucu! あー cute cute. Oke.
Cute! Ah, cute cute. Okay.
Really, is it cute though? かわいい？ Thank you!
Really, is it cute though? Cute? Thank you!
ありがとう！はぁ、疲れたね。
Thank you! Ha, that was tiring.
うーん、ポーズ、ポーズ。すくりしょ？すくりしょ？ん？ん？ん？はぁー...
Hm, pose, pose. Screenshot? Screenshot? Hm? Hm? Hm? Ha...
しゅっしゅっしゅっしゅっしゅっ... ありがとう。これ重いな。
Syu syu syu syu syu... thank you. This is heavy.
Ini berat loh guys, bentar guys ya. Mau simpan dulu. よいしょ。
This is heavy, guys, wait a second. I'm going to put it away. Heave-ho.
はぁー... はぁー... はぁー... 疲れ。おっけー。
Ha... ha... ha... tired. Okay.
Kita mau ngapain? Pose lagi? ん？ん？Mau apa? Mau apa?
What should we do? Pose again? Hm? Hm? What do you want? What do you want?
Mau ini? おぉー...
Want this? Oh...
あれがいいって、アイポーズ。どんなポーズ？ポーズ、ポーズ、ポーズ、ポーズ。
You said you liked that, the Ayu pose. What kind of pose? Pose, pose, pose, pose.
Halo Ioforia, halo Ioforia yang baru. Halo, welcome to KGC, welcome to Ioforia family!
Hello Ioforia, hello to the new Ioforia. Hello, welcome to KGC, welcome to the Ioforia family!
ハイ！ Apa mau apa lagi? おぉー... んー...
Hi! What else do you want? Oh... mm...
あーでもさー
Ah, but...
この後ゲスト来るかもしれない。どうしよう。
A guest might come after this. What should I do?
ゲストある？
Is there a guest?
Yofi te guest aru? Aru?
Yopi, is there a guest? Is there?
Eh, Yopinya guestnya siapa?
Eh, who's Yopi's guest?
Punya? Oh, punya!
Do I have one? Oh, I do!
It turns out I have a guest. Haha.
え、ゲスト誰かな？
Eh, who's the guest?
あ、あ、もしもし？
Ah, ah, hello?
Hello, pagi!
Hello, morning!
Hello! Hello!
どなたですか？ 誰です？
Who is it? Who are you?
ときのそらでーす！
It's Tokino Sora!
はい！ Yopiのお姉さんです！
Yes! I'm Yopi's big sister!
おめでとう 3D！
Congratulations on your 3D!
ありがとー！ Mwah mwah mwah!
Thank you! Mwah mwah mwah!
ということで、ありがとうね、わざわざ来てくれて。
Anyway, thank you for taking the time to come.
I love you! I love you!
恥ずかしい...
It's embarrassing...
ありがとう。本当に来てくれてありがとう。
Thank you. Thank you so much for coming.
絵、可愛いね。
The drawing is cute.
本当？ 本当？ Yopi、Yopiと可愛い？ 可愛い？ 可愛い？ これ。
Really? Really? Yopi, Yopi and this is cute? Cute? Cute? This.
Yopiちゃんはもう最高に可愛いから。
Yopi-chan is just the cutest.
ありがとう。
Thank you.
ということでね...
Anyway...
ねぇちゃん、ねぇちゃん、ねぇちゃん。
Big sister, big sister, big sister.
ねぇちゃん可愛い。
Big sister is cute.
せっかくお姉さんが来てくれたからね、ちょっとね、ゲームしたいと思います！
Since my big sister is here, I'd like to play a game!
お、ゲーム？ ゲーム？
Oh, a game? A game?
ここね、ちょっとちょうどこれとこれがあるから、ゲームしたいと思って。
Since we have this and this here, I thought we'd play a game.
ということで、ルール説明してもいいかな？
So, may I explain the rules?
OK! OK!
でお姉さんが始め何か、ものとか何でもいいけど、何か思い浮かぶものをちょっとYopiに言って。
First, big sister, think of something, anything is fine, and tell it to Yopi.
でもね、あの、ヒント、ヒントを出してくれればいいかな、と思って。
But, like, just give me some hints, I think.
Yopiがそのヒントを当てる... いい？
Yopi will guess it from the hints... Okay?
OK! OK! OK!
例えばね、そう、あの、小さくて可愛いものとか、あれって何だろう、何だろうって言ったら...
For example, if you say something "small and cute," and wonder "what is it?"...
あ、Yopiだのって。
...then "Ah, it's Yopi!"
Yopi、小さくて可愛いでしょ。
Yopi is small and cute, right?
可愛い。Yopiね可愛いね。うん。
Cute. Yopi is cute. Yeah.
で、何か何か思い浮かべたものあった？ もうある？
So, do you have something in mind? Already?
あ、なんか私的には...
Ah, as for me...
お姉さん的には？
As for big sister?
よく丸まってて可愛い、クマかなって思ったんだけど。
It's often curled up and cute, I thought maybe a bear.
ク、ク、クマ？ クマ？
A, a, a bear? A bear?
そうなんだよね。
That's right.
うちにもね、よく居るんだけどさ。
There's often one at my place too.
あー動物？
Ah, an animal?
動物、ベア。ベア。
An animal, a bear. A bear.
あー、ベア、そうなんだ。あの、もうちょっと、優しい、ものお願いします。
Ah, a bear, I see. Um, please make it something a bit more gentle.
じゃあ私もね、
Well, me too,
私のマスコットでもあるんだけど...
it's also my mascot...
クマさんです。
it's Mr. Bear.
クマ？ クマ？
Bear? Bear?
あ、よくね、バー、バーってよく言ってるんだよね。
Ah, it often says "bar, bar."
えーと何です？
Um, what is it?
どうなのよ。そのクマさん、Yopiちゃんが書いたらもう、100%可愛いんじゃないかなと思って、ちょっとその絵を家に飾りたいなーなんて思うんだけど。
What do you think? If Yopi-chan draws that bear, it'll be 100% cute, so I'd like to display that drawing in my house.
これ、これ飾る？ これ飾る？
Display this? Display this?
飾りたーい！
I want to display it!
待ってよ、これ、これ、お姉さんに渡すもんじゃないよ、もう。
Wait, this, this isn't something I should give to you, sister.
後でお姉さんちゃんと後で描いてくるので。今回はね...
I'll draw one properly for you later. For now...
ゲームやる、ゲームやりましょう。
Let's play the game. Let's play the game.
うーん、OK! じゃあ一つのヒント、お願いします。
Hmm, OK! Then one hint, please.
何？
What?
一つ目のヒント、えっと、クマさん、クマさん。
First hint... um, Mr. Bear, Mr. Bear.
あ、あれがヒントなーの？
Ah, is that the hint?
そう。そう。
Yes. Yes.
その、そのままクマだと思ってた。
I thought it was just "bear" as it is.
あ、そうなんだ。そうなんだ。え、始まってると思ってヒント全部言っちゃったよ。
Ah, I see. I see. Eh, I thought it had started and said all the hints!
えー！ あれがお試しだと思ってたー！
Eh! I thought that was a trial!
じゃあもう一回。あの、クマで、クマで、何？
Then one more time. Um, it's a bear, it's a bear, and what?
え、可愛くて。
Eh, it's cute.
可愛くて。じゃあ可愛いからラブラブしちゃう。
Cute. Well, since it's cute, I'll make it all lovey-dovey.
ラブラブしちゃって。で、その「バー、バー」って言ってる。
All lovey-dovey. And it says "bar, bar."
うちの、うちのマスコットなんだけど...
It's my, it's my mascot...
あ、わかるかなー？
Ah, I wonder if you know?
わかるよ、わかるよ。あと...
I know, I know. And...
昔はよく丸まってたんだ。Yopiちゃんとギュッてしてる絵とか、今度時間ある時...
It used to be all curled up. A picture of it hugging Yopi-chan... next time you have time...
あ、うん。書いてほしいなー！
Ah, yeah. I'd like you to draw that!
書く、書く。お姉さんと一緒に書くわ。
I'll draw it, I'll draw it. I'll draw it with you, sister.
やったー！
Yay!
ということで、あの、可愛い、顔がなんかモヨモヨしてる。今、うーん、どうしよう。
So, um, it's cute, the face is a bit fuzzy. Now, hmm, what to do.
Yopiちゃんが思うベアでいいよ。
Whatever bear Yopi-chan thinks is fine.
Yopiが思うベアでいい？ OK! Yopiが思う可愛い可愛いクマでいい？
Whatever bear Yopi thinks is fine? OK! Whatever cute bear Yopi thinks is fine?
OK!
これ、クマかどうかわかんないんだけど...
I don't know if this is a bear or not, but...
大丈夫。ちゃんとクマに見えるよ。
It's okay. It looks properly like a bear.
ちゃんと... あのね...
Properly... um, you know...
これ... ぬるね... くまに見える？
I'll paint this... does it look like a bear?
見える見える！
It does, it does!
うん、見える、くま、くま見える。
Yeah, I see it! A bear, I see a bear.
これアン肝ちゃんだよ。
This is Ankimo-chan.
うん、わかるよ。
Yeah, you can tell?
かわいいよ。
It's cute!
ほんと？
Really?
ほんと。
Really.
うん、今ピンクなんだけど。
Yeah, though it's pink right now.
だいじょうぶ。アン肝ちゃんピンクにもなるものだからだいじょうぶ。
It's okay. Ankimo-chan can be pink too, so it's fine.
あ、そうなの？ピンクにもなるの？
Oh, really? It can be pink?
うちの、うちの子は何でもできるからだいじょうぶ。
Our... our kid can do anything, so it's fine.
そうなんだ。いい子だね、もう。
I see. What a good kid. Truly...
いい子だよ。
Such a good kid.
ヨピちゃんの方が何倍もいい子よ。
Yopi-chan is many times better, though.
え？ヨピより？
Eh? Better than Yopi?
やばいな。
That's amazing.
やばい。ヨピの場所取られちゃう。
Amazing, right? It might take Yopi's place.
えーヨピちゃんはもう、もうキュートでビューティフルで...
But Yopi-chan is already cute and beautiful...
あ、ビューティフルで、私の妹だから、
And beautiful, and since she's my sister...
うん、妹だから、いつでも一緒。
Yeah, since she's my sister, we're always together.
あ、ありがとう！うれしい！
Ah, thank you! I'm so happy!
なもう泣くんじゃ、もう泣くよ。
I'm gonna cry, I'm crying!
あ泣いちゃう泣いちゃう、だめ！
Ah, she's crying, she's crying! No!
めっちゃかわいいね。
She's so cute.
ありがとう。これで合ってるね、アン肝ちゃん。
Thank you. This is correct, right? Ankimo-chan.
うん、ピンクだけど、ピンクだけど。
Yeah, even though it's pink, even though it's pink.
合ってる合ってる。
It's correct, it's correct.
ピンクだけど。
Even though it's pink.
ありがとう。ピンクでうれしいよきっと。
Thank you. I'm sure it's happy to be pink.
あよかった、うれしいね。ありがとう。
Good, glad you liked it. Thank you.
本当にありがとうございます。
Thank you so much, everyone.
これで正解ね。
So this is the answer.
改めて正解は...
Once again, the correct answer is...
正解 あん肝 Ankimo
Correct Answer: Ankimo
アン肝ちゃん！
Ankimo-chan!
イェーイ！アン肝ちゃん、ありがとう。
Yay! Ankimo-chan, thank you.
アン肝ちゃん。あ、そっか、これがいいるんだ、もうちょっと。
Ankimo-chan. Ah, right, I need this part too...
あ、そーだ、あとで顔描いとく。ごめんアン肝。
Wait, I'll draw the face too. Sorry, Ankimo.
かわいー！飾るよ！
Cute! I'll display it!
ありがとう。飾るこれ？
Thank you! Display this? Really?
うん！これ飾る。
Yeah! I'll display it.
プレゼントでしょ？うん。
It's a present, right? Yeah.
うん。そうだけど... 飾る？飾る？
Yeah. That's true, but... on display? Really?
飾る飾る。
I'll display it, definitely.
そうだよ。ありがとう。あとでフレーム付きで送ってあげる。
Yeah. Thank you! I'll send it with a frame later.
フレーム付きで。やったー！
With a frame! Yay!
ありがとう、お姉ちゃん！ありがとう。次は一緒にここで何かやろうね。
Thank you, big sis! Thank you. Let's do something here together next time.
やろうね。楽しみにしてるよ。
Let's! I'm looking forward to it.
ありがとう！I love you お姉ちゃん Love!
Thank you! I love you, big sis! Love!
I love you Yopi! I love you お姉ちゃん。
I love you, Yopi! I love you, sis!
んー、ま！
Mwah!
チュッ！ありがとう！本当におめでとう！
Mwah! Thank you! Congratulations, really!
ありがとう！お姉ちゃんの愛が...
Thank you! Big sis's love is...
え、次いるのかな？次いるのかな？
So, who's next? Is someone there?
Yopi ada guest lain gak sih?
Does Yopi have other guests?
Oh, cuma satu orang sih.
Oh, it's just one person.
Hai hai! Moshi moshi! Ada-ada, genzo? Eh, Bestie! Halo Bestie!
Hi hi! Hello! We're here! Bestie! Hello Bestie!
Welcome to gudang Yopi!
Welcome to Yopi's warehouse!
Woi! Bukan gudang!
Hey! It's not a warehouse!
Gak papa lah, udah capek.
It's fine, I'm already tired.
Rada kotor ya, mohon maaf.
It's a bit dirty, sorry about that.
Halo, selamat datang! Dengan siapa? Saya bicara dengan siapa?
Hello, welcome! With whom? With whom am I speaking?
Dengan siapa? Siapa duluan nih?
With whom? Who's first?
Oke oke, ayo kenalan dari suara. Ada Bobo!
Okay okay, let's introduce yourselves by voice. There's Bobo!
Iya, coba tebak. Ada Bobo tebak-tebakan Iru di sini!
Yeah, try to guess. Bobo is here to guess!
Terus ada, ada siapa lagi? Zeta?
And then, who else? Zeta?
Zeta? Bestie Zeta? Iya, Bestie Zeta!
Zeta? Bestie Zeta? Yeah, Bestie Zeta!
Wah! Wah! Terus ada, ada... temennya saya, saya, saya?
Wow! Wow! And then, there's... my friend, me, me?
Ada K-k-k-k-k-Gracie? Ollie!
Is it... K-k-k-Gracie? Ollie!
Sampai rose, Ollie? Iya, udah baru nih.
Finally, Ollie? Yeah, I'm all new.
Gimana? Lucu gak? Lucu gak?
How is it? Is it cute? Is it cute?
Lucu! Lucu! 3D-nya omedeto! Pretty-pretty!
Cute! Cute! Congrats on the 3D! Pretty-pretty!
Lucu lah, lucu lah! Selamat, selamat!
So cute! Congratulations!
Terima kasih, waduh, imut-imut... kalian, kalian lucu banget.
Thank you, wow, so cute... you guys are so cute.
Lebih lucu kalau Senpai rada nunduk dikit gitu, Ollie.
It would be cuter if Senpai bowed a bit, right Ollie?
Maksudnya bukan gitu?
Is that not what you meant?
Ah, gimana sih? Suka bener kadang-kadang.
Ah, what? You really like that sometimes.
Ya sudah lah, kita mau main game nih, guys. Kalian harus dijelasin dulu gak ininya?
Anyway, we're going to play a game, guys. Do I need to explain the rules?
Rule-nya? Enggak usah lah ya.
The rules? Probably not, right?
Kan kalian kan pinter kan? Bo, kamu pinter kan Bo?
You guys are smart, right? Bobo, you're smart, right?
Apa itu rule?
What are rules?
Oh, ya sudah, kamu turu. Ah, tapi ya udah lah.
Oh, then you sleep. But anyway.
Kalian bertiga kan ini ya, cerdas, cerdik, gitu kan?
The three of you are smart, clever, right?
Oke, nah, dari hint-hint ini siapa yang mau ngomong duluan?
Okay, now, from these hints, who wants to go first?
Siapa?
Who?
Aku deh! Boleh, boleh, aku!
I'll go! I'll go!
Oh, Zeta! Apa nih, Jet?
Oh, Zeta! What is it?
Nih hint dari aku.
Here's a hint from me.
Hint pertama dari aku adalah...
First hint from me is...
Teretetet...
Drumroll...
Bobo, lu apa sih?
Bobo, what are you doing?
Langsung...
Straight to it...
Amis!
Fishy!
Ha? Manis?
Huh? Sweet?
Amis! Amis! Amis! Amis!
Fishy! Fishy! Fishy! Fishy!
Amis, amis? くさい！くさい！
Fishy, fishy? Stinky! Stinky!
あ、くま、あ、くま、あ、あ、あ...
Ah, bear, ah, bear, ah, ah, ah...
Aduh, gimana... aku mau gambar amis gimana coba?
Oh boy, how... how am I supposed to draw "fishy"?
Ya udah...
Okay then...
Amis, amis gimana sih?
How fishy is it?
Ya udahlah, ini... masa nggak tahu sih?
Oh well, this... how can you not know?
Iya amislah...
Yes, it's fishy...
Ih bau gitu... mm... gitu.
It's smelly... mm... like that.
Berimajinasi.
Use your imagination.
Ya, oke, next-lah. Aduh, ini apa sih?
Okay, next. Oh, what's this?
Oke, hint dari Ollie kali ya?
Okay, a hint from Ollie maybe?
Nih, ini kalau sampai denger...
Here, if you hear this...
Ollie hanya ingin mengonfirmasi...
Ollie just wants to confirm...
Exactly, it's exactly what you think it is.
Licin.
Slippery.
Ha? Ollie apa?
Huh? Ollie what?
Licin.
Slippery.
Licin, licin, licin! Licin!
Slippery, slippery, slippery! Slippery!
Sangat harus banget itu.
That's a must.
Aduh, aku... aku takut, aku takut.
Oh, I... I'm afraid, I'm afraid.
Bo... bo... tambah ada, Bu, sama yang kamu.
Mo... mo... there's more, Bu, with yours.
Tambah deh, apa? Aku takut.
Add it, what is it? I'm afraid.
Ya udah, ini...
Okay, this...
Kalau lu masih belum bisa, kebangetan banget sih.
If you still can't get it, it's really too much.
Aduh!
Oh!
Ya, gimana... licin.
Well, how... slippery.
Petunjuk terakhir. Nih ya.
Last hint. Here it is.
Tadi amis, udah licin, udah. Sekarang...
It was fishy, already slippery, done. Now...
Berkumis.
Mustachioed.
Woah!
Licin, berkumis... kebayang nggak sih?
Slippery, mustachioed... can you imagine?
Sempurna.
Perfect.
Emang apa tuh? Emang apa tuh?
What is it? What is it?
Emang aku tahu!
I do know!
Itu lho, bapak-bapak yang... haha!
You know, like a middle-aged man who... haha!
Bapak-bapak habis mandi pakai losion gitu.
A middle-aged man after a bath using lotion.
Beda! Beda! Beda bener!
Different! Different! Totally different!
Oi, oi, oi. Berkumis.
Hey, hey, hey. Mustachioed.
Emang amis, amis berarti ikan kan? Ikan kan?
It's fishy, fishy means fish, right? A fish, right?
Hmm... apa ya?
Hmm... what is it?
Aduh amis, Bestie, amis, amis.
Oh fishy, Bestie, fishy, fishy.
Apa ya? Ah, oke deh, oke deh.
What is it? Ah, okay then, okay then.
Tapi, tapi... oke, aku boleh ngomong nggak nih?
But, but... okay, can I say it?
Amis, licin, berkumis. Betul?
Fishy, slippery, mustachioed. Right?
He-eh.
Yeah.
Berkumisnya penting.
The mustache is important.
Ollie! Bukan Ollie!
Ollie! Not Ollie!
Bukan Ollie... Ah!
Not Ollie... Ah!
Lele, lele, lele, lele!
Catfish, catfish, catfish, catfish!
Lele...
Catfish...
Lele jawabannya?
Catfish is the answer?
Lele!
Catfish!
Emang iya?
Is it really?
Nggak tahu... lah aku nanya balik sih?
I don't know... why am I asking back?
Nggak yakin?
Not sure?
Yakin! Udah yakin apa belum?
Sure! Are you sure yet or not?
Dah yakin, ayo cepat apa?
Sure, come on, quick, what is it?
Ya udah, hmm... jawabannya adalah...
Okay, hmm... the answer is...
Lele!
Catfish!
Pintar banget kalian ini.
You guys are so smart.
Iya, lele. Aku tadi sempat... sempat kepikirannya anu, yang cokelat, terus itu...
Yes, catfish. I... I briefly thought of that, the brown one, and then...
正解 ナマズ Catfish
Correct Answer: Catfish
Anu yang cokelat? Apa? Apa?
That brown one? What? What?
Emang tetap ya lele ada yang warna cokelat ya. Okelah.
Catfish can definitely be brown. Okay.
Oh iya, iya, iya, iya. Iya, iya, iya.
Oh yes, yes, yes, yes. Yes, yes, yes.
Aduh.
Oh.
Tadi pas denger amis aja Ollie dengernya, 'Hah, ketek?'
When I heard fishy, I heard it as, 'Huh, armpit?'
Amis!
Fishy!
Taruh di ketek gini. Mm... mm...
Put it in the armpit like this. Mm... mm...
Langsung berketek-ketek ente, Senpai.
You're immediately all about armpits, Senpai.
Mohon maaf. Kalau itu contohin dong yang nggak amis gimana.
My apologies. If so, show us an example of how not to be fishy.
Oh, oke, oke. Punya Yopi, punya Yopi.
Oh, okay, okay. Yopi's, Yopi's.
Auw! Auw!
Oke, makasih, Besties!
Okay, thanks, Besties!
Ih, kohaiya lucu banget deh. Mm... mm...
Oh, kohaiya is so cute. Mm... mm...
Cu-cu-cu-cu.
Congrats ya 3D-nya!
Congrats on your 3D!
Ih, makasih banyak, Besties!
Oh, thank you so much, Besties!
Makasih sudah datang. I love you semua!
Thanks for coming. I love you all!
Semangat, sama-sama!
Good luck, you're welcome!
I love you. Mwah! Bye bye!
Love you. Bye bye. Mwah, mwah, mwah!
Mwah, mwah, mwah! Bye bye, Cebol!
Mwah, mwah, mwah! Bye bye, Shorty!
Apa lo panggil gue Cebol?
What did you call me, Shorty?
Lah!
Wait!
Ih apa sih, Cebol dibilang Cebol. Aduh capek.
What the, Shorty called Shorty. Oh, I'm tired.
Sekarang...
Now...
一緒、ちょっと運動しようかな？
Together, should I do some exercise?
Kita, kita senam-senam kali ya? Aduh capek. Oke.
We, maybe we should do some stretching? Oh, I'm tired. Okay.
Satu... dua... tiga, tiga, tiga.
One... two... three, three, three.
あれ？誰？誰？
Huh? Who is it? Who is it?
Yopi!
Apa sayang? Apa kenapa sayang? Apa kenapa sayang?
What is it, dear? What's wrong, dear? What's wrong, dear?
Mau bobo... mau bobo di sini.
Want to sleep... want to sleep here.
Hah, aduh gimana jadinya?
Huh, oh how's that gonna work?
Jadi Moona tuh ya...
So Moona, right...
Udah keliling-keliling rumah...
Has gone all around the house...
Nggak ketemu piggy bank-nya Moona.
Can't find Moona's piggy bank.
Oh gitu?
Is that so?
Oh my God. Mau cari? Mau cari di sini?
Oh my God. Want to look? Want to look here?
Iya, ya udah ayo cari.
Yes, okay then let's look.
Mana ya?
Where is it?
Tapi di sini nggak ada, tuh.
But it's not here, look.
Enggak ada.
It's not here.
いないんたって、 nggak ada.
It's not here, I told you.
Aduh, aduh, aduh, aduh...
Oh, dear, dear, dear...
あに…
What...
Enggak ada, tuh. Enggak ada.
Not here, see. Not here.
Tuh, nggak ada. Tuh, nggak ada.
Look, not here. Look, not here.
Yah, nggak ada, tuh. Celengan kamu udah nggak ada di sini.
Well, it's not here. Your piggy bank is no longer here.
Ngapain?
What now?
Bosen. Ya udah, jadi kamera aja deh sana.
Bored. Okay then, just be the camera over there.
Ya udah, sini!
Okay, come here!
Mana mau jadi kamera katanya. Ya udah. Oke. Dah.
Where? You said you wanted to be the camera. Okay then. Okay. Done.
Gimana, Beb?
How is it, Babe?
Hi, I... since I'm the cameraman right now...
I want to see everything that you got.
Okay, dari bawah. Iya, oke, Bestie.
Okay, from below. Yes, okay, Bestie.
Ooh... woah!
Halo dari bawah.
Hello from below.
Hi! Hi!
Hi! Mm... Hi!
Ah!
Dah, ah. Pegal jadi cameraman ternyata.
That's enough. It's tiring being a cameraman, it turns out.
Moh... amoh... pegal.
Ugh... so tired... sore.
Gimana gimana kalau kalau...
How about if... if...
...kalau kita nyanyi?
...if we sing?
Gak mau.
I don't want to.
Ayo dong!
Come on!
Aku tuh tadi jadinya gak mau nyanyi!
I said I didn't want to sing!
Gak mau!
I don't want to!
Kenapa kenapa sih aku... harusnya aku bikin io salah...
Why... I should have made Io's mistake...
...terus ngebottakin kamu di sini tau gak!
...and then made you bald here, you know!
Eh ya udah ya udah ya udah.
Eh okay, okay, okay.
Katanya Moona mau nyanyi.
Moona said she wanted to sing.
Iya, iya. I want to sing.
Yes, yes. I want to sing.
Sing what?
Apa ya?
What should it be?
Bentar. Moona lupa mau nyanyi lagu apa.
Wait. Moona forgot what song she wanted to sing.
Apa deh? Lagu-lagu lagu jadul? Jadul?
What? Some old songs? Old songs?
Lagu lagu... lagu...
Songs... songs...
Lagu itu lho, yang gini.
That song, you know, the one like this.
Oh yang gini! Yang gini!
Oh like this! Like this!
Apa... apa namanya Moona lupa...
What... what's it called? Moona forgot...
So... ra... a... na... na... na... na... na... na...
Oh judulnya! Blue Bird!
Oh the title! Blue Bird!
Oh iya! Blue Bird!
Oh yeah! Blue Bird!
Let's go!
Let's go! Kita bilang 'seno' Blue Bird, oke?
Let's go! We'll say 'seno' for Blue Bird, okay?
Oke 'seno' gitu oke?
Okay, like 'ready-go', okay?
Seno! Blue Bird!
Ready! Blue Bird!
飛翔（はばた）いたら　戻らないと言って
If you spread your wings, say you won't return
目指したのは　蒼い　蒼い　あの空
What you aimed for was that blue, blue sky
ブルーバード
いきものがかり
Lyrics・Composition：水野良樹
Blue Bird
Ikimonogakari
Lyrics & Composition: Yoshiki Mizuno
“悲しみ”はまだ覚えられず　“切なさ”は今掴み始めた
I still haven't learned "sadness", I've just started to grasp "heartache"
あなたへと抱くこの感情も　今“言葉”に変わっていく
Even these feelings I hold for you are now turning into "words"
未知なる世界の遊夢（ゆめ）から目覚めて
Awakening from a dream of an unknown world
この羽根を広げ　飛び立つ
I'll spread these wings and take flight
飛翔（はばた）いたら　戻らないと言って
If you spread your wings, say you won't return
目指したのは　白い　白い　あの雲
What you aimed for were those white, white clouds
突き抜けたら　みつかると知って
Knowing that if you break through, you'll find it
振り切るほど
To the point of shaking it off
蒼い　蒼い　あの空
That blue, blue sky
愛想尽きたような音で　錆びついた古い窓は壊れた
With a sound like it's fed up, the old rusty window broke
見飽きたカゴは　ほら捨てていく　振り返ることはもうない
Look, I'm throwing away the cage I'm tired of seeing, I won't look back anymore
高鳴る鼓動に　呼吸をあずけて
Entrusting my breath to my thumping heart
この窓を蹴って　飛び立つ
I'll kick this window and take flight
駆け出したら　手にできると言って
If you start running, say you can make it
いざなうのは　遠い　遠い　あの声
What invites you is that far, far-off voice
眩しすぎた　あなたの手も握って
Gripping your hand which was too dazzling
求めるほど
To the point of seeking it
蒼い　蒼い　あの空
That blue, blue sky
堕ちていくと　わかっていた
I knew I was falling
それでも　光を追い続けていくよ
Even so, I'll keep chasing the light
飛翔（はばた）いたら　戻らないと言って
If you spread your wings, say you won't return
目指したのは　白い　白い　あの雲
What you aimed for were those white, white clouds
突き抜けたら　みつかると知って
Knowing that if you break through, you'll find it
振り切るほど
To the point of shaking it off
蒼い　蒼い　あの空
That blue, blue sky
Ini ini kita kayak karaokean biasa.
This is just like our usual karaoke.
Aduh.
Ouch.
Capek, beneran?
Tired, for real?
Mau makan?
Want to eat?
Enggak.
No.
Engga sih... Karena... karena kamu cape, Moona ada rekomendasi.
No... Because... because you're tired, Moona has a recommendation.
Iya, apa? Ambil-ambil.
Yes, what is it? Go get it.
Guys, sori, guys. Apa? Ada apa?
Guys, sorry, guys. What? What's up?
Apa? Ada apa? Aaa!
What? What's up? Ahhh!
Ready? Ready?
Wangi wangi wangi!
Smells good, smells good, smells good!
Biar wangi! Wah!
To make it smell good! Wah!
Dah beres! Sini, sini!
All done! Come here, come here!
Udah pake! Keren!
I've used it! Cool!
Keren banget nih! Nih.
This is so cool! Here.
Ini tuh bukan deodorant, ini tuh koyo!
This isn't deodorant, this is a pain relief patch!
Ini tuh koyo versi cair yang kamu pake!
This is a liquid version of a pain relief patch that you used!
Aduh udah udah... udah mendingan, udah mendingan.
Ouch, okay, okay... it's better, it's better now.
Oke, aman kan ya?
Okay, it's safe, right?
Aman...
Safe...
Makasih Airani. Moona cape, Moona mau ke kamar Moona ah.
Thanks Airani. Moona is tired, Moona wants to go to Moona's room.
Eh bentar-bentar! Ada sesuatu bentar.
Eh, wait, wait! There's something, just a second.
Kita mau kasih sesuatu dulu.
We want to give you something first.
Oh iya! Ah!
Oh, right! Ah!
Eh besok ada apa? Besok ada apa? Besok ada apa?
Eh, what's tomorrow? What's tomorrow? What's tomorrow?
Besok! Besok ada apa ya?
Tomorrow! What's tomorrow?
Kokocari kan? Kokocaro!
It's Kokocari, right? Kokocaro!
Oke, 3-2-1 deh, oke?
Okay, 3-2-1 then, okay?
Three, two, one, zero!
RISU!!!
Risu! Lho kok gini banget?
Risu! Why is it like this?
Iya kok di-notice?
Yeah, why was it noticed?
Kaya... Risu lagi ngapain sih?
Like... what is Risu doing?
3D Showcase Risu, September tanggal 18 besok.
Risu's 3D Showcase, September 18th tomorrow.
Jamnya sama guys! Jam 8, jam 8.
The time is the same, guys! 8 o'clock, 8 o'clock.
Jangan lupa ya! Tomorrow! Yeah!
Don't forget! Tomorrow! Yeah!
Yeah jangan lupa ya! Jangan lupa.
Yeah, don't forget! Don't forget.
Posenya!
The pose!
Pose gimana tadi?
How was the pose earlier?
Uuuh! So so innocent banget sih Risu!
Uuuh! Risu looks so, so innocent!
Gitu ya? Dah ah... Moona cape.
Is that so? That's enough... Moona's tired.
Sumpah, Moona mau turun.
Seriously, Moona wants to head down.
Ya udah. Thank you. I love you baby!
Alright then. Thank you. I love you, baby!
Mwah, mwah, mwah.
Oh! Bye, I love you baby! Mwah.
Tinggal sendiri. Gimana ya?
I'm all alone now. What should I do?
一人だけだから... まあいっか。
Since I'm alone... oh well.
じゃ、外行こうか？
Then, shall we go outside?
Kita keluar ya guys.
Let's head out, guys.
See you!
See you, mwah!
NOW PAINTING
Iya sori ya, abis ya.
Yes, sorry, it's over.
ということで、イオフィ一応アイドルだから
So, since Iofi is an idol after all,
ちょっとコールアンドレスポンスというものをやりたい。
I want to do a little something called call and response.
したいと思います。
I would like to do...
So I want to try the... what do I want to call it again? Call and response, okay?
Jadi kalau Yopi bilang, "Ioforia!", kalian "Obisa!", ya?
So if Yopi says "Ioforia!", you guys "Obisa!", okay?
Okay, ya? Ippatsu de ii yo ne?
Okay, right? Just once is fine, right?
Ippatsu de ii? Okay. Ikee?
Just once? Okay. Ready?
Kita coba, coba sekali. Okay?
Let's try, try once. Okay?
Yopi lihat loh, Yopi lihat ya.
Yopi is watching, Yopi is watching.
I'm see... I'm seeing this. All of this, okay?
We're gonna do it once. Just one time, okay?
Ippatsu de iku yo? Ikeru? Okay.
Going for it once? Ready? Okay.
じゃ、イオフォリア！
Then, Ioforia!
OBISA!
どう？どう？Okay.
How was it? How was it? Okay.
Okay! Okay!
うわ！え？え？
Whoa! Huh? Huh?
え？え？！
Huh? Huh?!
え？ Apa ini? Banyak banget! ちょっとまって！
Eh? What is this? There are so many! Wait a minute!
これについて... 愛...
About this... love...
おいっしょ... ダダダダダダダン！
There we go... Ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-dah!
Bentar... mana ini depannya? おいっしょ。
Wait... where is the front? There we go.
Hi!
Hi! Hi! Hi, hi, hi!
Liquid solid... ah.
え？はいこっちポーズとる。んん。
Eh? Come here, let's pose. M-m.
でもさ、これさ、イオフォリアの愛の形だからちょっと小さいな。
But you know, since this is the shape of Ioforia's love, it's a bit small.
Jadi itu kayak ibaratnya cinta kalian ke Yopi, tapi kok kecil ya?
So it's like your love for Yopi, but why is it small?
Bisa digedein nggak? Bisa digedein nggak? Hm?
Can it be made bigger? Can it be made bigger? Hm?
大きくできる？もっとイオフィの愛に... 愛をね。
Can you make it bigger? More of Yopi's love... love.
Can you make it bigger, the love? So this is kind of like my love... which is Ioforia's love for me, so can you make it bigger? M-hm?
Gimana? Obisa? Obisa? Obisa?
How? Obisa? Obisa? Obisa?
あ... Okay.
Ah... Okay.
ドゥン！あれ、あれ？
Boom! Oh, wait?
Okay, うわ！
Okay, whoa!
Wih! Berat... んん... うわ！
Whoa! Heavy... nnn... uwa!
大きいな！
It's big!
Yopi bilang besar sih, tapi nggak sebesar ini masalahnya.
Yopi did say big, but the problem is it's not this big.
Gimana?
What now?
Hi! Haha! Hi!
チクタク... Haha.
Tick-tock... Haha.
え？これ大きいけど。あ？これだけ？これだけ？
Eh? This is big though. Ah? Is this all? Is this all?
もっと見せて！はい！
Show me more! Yes!
Mana, mana, mana, mana, mana cintanya? え！
Where, where, where, where, where is the love? Eh!
Gila! Ahaha!
Crazy! Ahaha!
Eh, bentar. あれ？あれ？
Eh, wait. Huh? Huh?
え、ちょちょちょちょちょ！怖い、怖い！助けて！
Eh, wa-wa-wa-wa-wait! Scary, scary! Help!
助けて！助けて！み... ああ！
Help! Help! Mi... aaa!
ああああ！
Aaaa!
Halo, Ioforia!
Hello, Ioforia!
Ioforia, Ioforia, Ioforia! いいげむす...
Ioforia, Ioforia, Ioforia! How cute...
ようこそ！
Welcome!
Halo, selamat datang!
Hello, welcome!
Ini kita udah ganti ya. Hai! Aduh, cantik banget ya. Hai!
We've changed now. Hi! Oh, it's so beautiful. Hi!
きれいだね！Hehe.
It's beautiful, isn't it! Hehe.
ということであの、今日は3Dになったのでやりたいことがあります。
And so, since I'm 3D today, there's something I want to do.
So there's something I really, really want to do when I have this... 3D and these fingers. Hehe.
Jadi ada satu hal yang Yopi pengen coba kalau udah punya tangan, tangan dan body, dan body kayak gini.
So there's one thing Yopi wants to try now that I have hands, hands and a body, and a body like this.
Kalian tahu nggak? Masih ingat nggak? Masih ingat? Do you remember?
Do you know? Do you still remember? Do you remember? Do you remember?
あの、覚えてる、覚えてる、覚えてる？あの、覚えてる人いる？いる？
Um, do you remember, remember, remember? Um, is there anyone who remembers? Anyone?
あ、よかった！Haha.
Ah, thank goodness! Haha.
ということでやりたいのは、手話！Sign language! Halo!
And so, what I want to do is, sign language! Sign language! Hello!
でもさ、手話もね、いろんな種類があって。
But you know, there are many types of sign language.
で今日はね、日本語と、えっと、英語の、あのAmerican Sign Languageをやりたいと思います。
And today, I'd like to do Japanese and, um, English, um, American Sign Language.
So I'm gonna do American Sign Language and a little bit of Japanese Sign Language.
So hi, guys!
Thank you for coming here.
I really, really appreciated it. Thank you, thank you. Mwah, mwah, mwah, mwah, mwah, mwah!
ということで本当にありがとう. Thank you.
And so, thank you very much. Thank you.
So really, really I love you all. I really love you all. Hi, I love you all.
Thank you for supporting me. Thank you.
So I am...
Let me introduce myself again. 自己紹介いい？自己紹介いい？
Let me introduce myself again. Is it okay to self-introduce? Is it okay to self-introduce?
いいの？いいの？
Is it okay? Is it okay?
Okay. 自己紹介いって！
Okay. Self-introduction time!
So thank you. My name is I-O-F-I.
Iofi. It's nice to meet you.
So I want to sing some language for you... I want to sing some song. Oh my god, I'm so nervous.
ということで今日はねちょっと手話で歌いたい曲があるのよ。んん。
So today, there's a song I want to sing a bit with sign language. M-m.
So then I want to sing something for you. So after this, please listen. Ne?
聞いてください。
Please listen.
僕が君の耳になる。
I'll be your ears.
僕が君の耳になって君の一部になる
I'll be your ears so that I can become a part of you
そんな夢を今叶えたい
I want to make such a dream come true right now
叶えたい
...want to make it come true.
声は聞こえなくても 愛が響いている
Love can echo through the air even though you can't hear my voice
そんな君をずっと 愛してる
I'll always be in love with you
僕が君の耳になる
Lyrics: HANDSIGN Composition: 中村泰輔
Boku ga Kimi no Mimi ni Naru
Lyrics: HANDSIGN Composition: Taisuke Nakamura
君が見ている景色 僕も見えるといいな
I wish I could experience what you see
手と手重なり合って 君に夢中になった
Holding hand in hand made me crazy about you
聞こえないことで僕らは 聞こえないことで二人は
By nothing being able to hear each other
もっと知りたい 言葉にして
I want to know more about you, in words
モノクロだった世界中が
The once monochrome world
鮮やかな色に変わった
is now colored wonderfully
君が好きだよ どんな時も
I love you, no matter what
溢れる思い 奏でるよ
I'll always play with these overflowing feelings
僕が君の耳になる 君の一つになれる
I'll be your ears so that I can become a part of you
そんな夢を今 叶えたい
I want to make such a dream come true right now
声は聞こえなくても 愛が響いている
Love can echo through the air even though you can't hear my voice
そんな君をずっと 愛してる
I'll always be in love with you
君と見てきた景色 雨が降る日もあった
I've shared some rainy days with you
ふと見せる涙の意味を 僕もしれるといいな
I wish I knew the meaning of your tears
くだらないことで僕らは くだらないことで二人は
We hurt each other over silly things
傷つけあって 本当にごめんね
I'm really sorry that I hurt you
どんな風にすれば二人
How does a relationship between two people able to
いつまでも 愛し合えるままでいれるかな
continue to love each other and last forever?
君がいるから 頑張れるよ
I'm able to continue because of you
支えてくれて ありがとう
Thank you for supporting me
僕が君の耳になる 君の一つになれる
I'll be your ears so that I can become a part of you
そんな夢を今 叶えたい
I want to make such a dream come true right now
声が聞こえなくても 愛が響いている
Love can echo through the air even though you can't hear my voice
そんな君といま
Even now, be with you
僕の手が枯れてゆくまで
I swear I'll keep you safe until my hands wither
君を守り続けると誓うよ
100年経って 来世にだって
Forever and ever, even after a century,
いつまでも 永遠に
or in the afterlife, forever and ever
僕が君の耳になる 君の一つになれる
I'll be your ears so that I can become a part of you
そんな夢を今 叶えたい
I want to make such a dream come true right now
声が聞こえなくても 愛が響いている
Love can echo through the air even though you can't hear my voice
そんな君といま
Even now, be with you
僕が君の耳になる 君の一つになれる
I'll be your ears so that I can become a part of you
そんな夢を今 叶えたい
I want to make such a dream come true right now
声は聞こえなくても 愛が響いている
Love can echo through the air even though you can't hear my voice
そんな君をずっと 愛してる
I'll always be in love with you
ODDS&ENDS
Lyrics + Composition: ryo (supercell)
Lyrics・Composition: ryo (supercell)
いつだって君は笑われものだ
You were always an object of laughter.
やることなすことツイてなくて
Whatever you did, you were out of luck.
挙げ句に雨に降られて
On top of that, you got caught in the rain.
お気に入りの傘は風で飛んでって
Your favorite umbrella flew away in the wind.
そこの野良犬はご苦労様と
A stray dog over there said "tough luck"...
足をふんづけてった
...and stepped on your foot.
Ah...
いつも通り君は嫌われものだ
As usual, you're an outcast.
何もせずとも遠ざけられて
Kept at a distance without doing anything.
努力をしてみるけれど
Even though you try your best...
その理由なんて「なんとなく」で
The reason for it is "just because"...
君は途方に暮れて悲しんでた
You were at a loss and feeling sad.
ならあたしの声を使えばいいよ
Then you should just use my voice.
人によっては理解不能で
For some people, it's incomprehensible.
なんて耳障り、ひどい声だって
They might say it's jarring, a terrible voice.
言われるけど
But...
きっと君の力になれる
I'm sure I can be of help to you.
だからあたしを歌わせてみて
So please let me sing.
そう君の、君だけの言葉でさ
With your, and only your, words.
綴って連ねて
Spell it out, line it up.
あたしがその言葉を叫ぶから
Because I'll scream those words.
描いて理想を
Draw your ideals.
その思いは誰にも触れさせない
I won't let anyone touch those feelings.
ガラクタの声はそして響く
And so, the voice of junk resounds.
ありのまま不器用につないで
Connecting clumsily, just as it is.
精一杯に声をあげる
Giving its all to raise its voice.
いつからか君は人気ものだ
Before you knew it, you were popular.
たくさんの人に持てはやされ
Flattered by so many people.
あたしも鼻が高い
I'm proud of you too.
でもいつからか君は変わった
But somewhere along the line, you changed.
冷たくなって、だけど寂しそうだった
You became cold, but you seemed lonely.
「もう機械の声なんてたくさんだ
"I've had enough of this machine's voice.
僕は僕自身なんだよ」って
I am my own self!"
ついに君は抑えきれなくなって
Finally, you couldn't hold it back anymore...
あたしを嫌った
...and you hated me.
君の背後で誰かが言う
Behind your back, someone says,
「虎の威を借る狐の虚勢」と
"A fox parading in the tiger's skin."
君は一人で泣いてたんだね
You were crying all alone, weren't you?
聞こえる？この声
Can you hear it? This voice.
あたしがその言葉をかき消すから
Because I'll drown out those words.
解ってる？本当は
Do you realize? The truth is...
君が誰より優しいってことを
...that you're kinder than anyone else.
ガラクタの声はそして歌う
And so, the voice of junk sings.
他の誰でもない君のために
For no one else but you.
軋んでいく限界も超えて
Surpassing even the creaking limits.
二人はどれにたくさんの
The two of us, how many...
言葉を思い付いたことだろう
...words did we think of?
だけど今は何一つ思い付かなくて
But now I can't think of a single one.
だけど何もかも解った
But I understood everything.
「そうか、きっとこれは夢だ。
"I see, this must be a dream.
永遠に醒めない、君と会えた、
A dream from which I'll never wake, where I met you,
そんな夢」
...that kind of dream."
ガラクタは幸せそうな顔をしたまま
The piece of junk, with a happy face...
どれだけ呼んでももう動かない
...won't move anymore, no matter how much you call.
望んだはずの結末に
At the ending you must have wished for,
君は泣き叫ぶ
...you scream out.
「嘘だろ、嘘だろ」って泣き叫ぶ
Screaming, "It's a lie, it's a lie!"
「僕は無力だ。
"I am powerless.
ガラクタ一つだって救えやしない」
I can't even save a single piece of junk."
思いは涙に
Feelings turn into tears...
ぽつりぽつりとその頬を濡らす
...wetting those cheeks bit by bit.
その時世界は
At that moment, the world...
途端にその色を大きく変える
...suddenly changes its color greatly.
悲しみ　喜び
Sadness, joy,
全てを独りと一つは知った
The lonely one and the single one knew it all.
言葉は歌になりこの世界を
Words become song, and throughout this world,
再び駆け巡る君のために
they race again for your sake.
その声に意思を宿して
Investing that voice with a will,
今、思いが響く
now, the feelings resound.
（笑い・ため息）
(Laughing and sighing)
はぁ… 会えたね！
Hah... We finally met!
あだっ… 大丈夫？ オッケー、私大丈夫。
Ouch... Are you okay? Okay, I'm okay.
あ、これ取っておきました。これ要る。
Ah, I kept this. I need this.
Minal Aidin wal-Faizin! はい… はい！
Happy Eid Mubarak! Yes... Yes!
ということで… はぁ… 全部やっておきました。
So... hah... I've done everything.
Yopi udah lakuin apa yang Yopi pengen. Dah deh aman.
Yopi has done everything she wanted. It's safe now.
あぁ、何でこのBGMなの… 泣いちゃう…
Oh man, why is this the BGM? It's so emotional...
So I want to just really really say thank you, thank you, thank you all for supporting me...
...for two... almost three years, right? It's almost three years.
Thank you makasih udah men-support, udah meng-oshi, udah apa sih mendorong Yopi selama tiga tahun...
Thank you for supporting me, for being my fan, for pushing Yopi forward for these three years...
…hampir tiga tahun ya, tiga tahun ini ya. Makasih.
...almost three years, right? These three years. Thank you.
ということで本当に… えっとマネージャーさんも。
So, really... um, my manager as well.
マネージャー泣いてる？ 今泣いてる？ え、Mちゃん泣いてるって？
Manager, are you crying? Crying right now? Eh, is M-chan crying?
マネージャーありがとう。
Manager, thank you.
あの本当に皆さんホロライブの全体皆さんありがとう。本当に仲良くしてくれてありがとう。
Really, thank you to everyone at Hololive. Thank you so much for being so friendly.
ホロスターズのみんなもありがとうございます。
And to everyone at Holostars, thank you very much.
えっとマネージャーちゃんとみつみママ、えっとlackパパ、Viviママ...
Manager-chan, Mitsumi-mama, lack-papa, Vivi-mama...
…とあのYAGOO、ありがとう！
...and YAGOO, thank you!
Yopiをホロライブインドネシア一期生として受け入れてくれてありがとう。
Thank you for accepting Yopi as a Hololive Indonesia 1st Gen member.
あのYAGOO大好きだよ。うん、何回言ってもだけど、大好きだよ。Makasih Bang.
YAGOO, I love you. No matter how many times I say it, I love you. Thank you, sir.
Okay, jadi habis ini kita sayang sekali lagu terakhir...
Okay, so after this, unfortunately, it's the final song...
Jadi udah siap? Ini bakal jadi call-and-response terakhir. Okay?
Are you ready? This will be the last call-and-response. Okay?
本当に今日ありがとう。じゃあ…
Thank you so much for today. Well...
最後の曲行きたいと思います。
I'd like to move on to the final song.
聴いてください。Q&A=E!
Please listen: Q&A=E!
予想外 question
Unexpected question
想定外 answer
Unpredictable answer
せーの！ Clap your hands!
Ready! Clap your hands!
恋しちゃうかも
I might fall in love
暗作な世界に
In this pitch-black world
好きっていいでしょう？
It's okay to say I love you, right?
私色に染まる
Stained in my own colors
ちょいちょいちょいでしょう？
Easy as pie, right?
イタズラな princess
Mischievous princess
本気だっちゃおうもん！
I'm getting serious!
おんなじ想いかな？
Do you feel the same way?
もっと近くにいたいの
I want to be closer to you
でも待っているだけなんて ヨヨヨつまらない
But just waiting around is so, so, so boring
変わらない宝物
An unchanging treasure
宇宙で一番...
The best in the universe...
思っちゃうよね どっちゃうよね 恋しちゃえば
You'll think so, you'll be puzzled, if you fall in love
私らしさ
Being myself
ふねえみちゃうような まじちゃうなら 試しちゃおう
Getting lost, if we're serious, let's give it a try
未来 未来
Future, future
まだまだ持っちゃうのに 踊っちゃうのに 笑ってほしい
I'm still holding on, still dancing, but I want you to smile
それ君だから
Because it's you
わかっちゃうよね あっちゃうよね 決めしちゃおう
You'll understand, we'll meet, let's decide it
Question? Answer!
大好きだもん
Because I love you
そんなんドドって言うよ
I'll say it loud and clear
もう頷んでいいかな？
Is it okay to nod now?
見ていてほしいの
I want you to watch me
Just tell me, tell me
tell me, tell me
飛び込んじゃえ もっともっともっと
Jump in, more and more
もっともっともっと
and more and more
照らしちゃえ ほらほらほら
Illuminate it, look look look
ほらほらほら
look look look
甘えちゃい寄り添っちゃい
Spoiling, snuggling
言っちゃえば私らしさ
If I say it, that's so me
夢見ちゃいような逃げちゃいような
Like a dream, like running away
大好きな未来 未来の
The future I love
思っちゃいついに 思っちゃいついに
Finally I think, finally I think
笑ってほしい
I want you to smile
そう 君だから
Yes, because it's you
分かっちゃいような 合っちゃいような
Like knowing, like matching
イメージちゃい ばっちょばっちょ
Imaging patcho-patcho
Utarakan dari milikmu
Express it from yours
Give me love, Give me love
Mitsumau mitsumau
Staring at each other
Stay love, I love me
Abunau we all about love
Watch out, we're all about love
Give me love, Give me love
バイバイ～
Bye-bye!